# **BIJAN MAZAHERI**

Q github.com/honeybijan S bijanmazaheri.com ■ bmazaher@caltech.edu
Pasadena, CA (781)-985-0881

I am a computer scientist and mathematician interested in the synthesis and transportability of knowledge from and between multiple data sources. My work spans the fields of causality, data fusion, and distribution shift. I am currently pursuing a Ph.D. in Computing and Mathematical Sciences at Caltech supported by a NSF Graduate Research Fellowship and an Amazon AI4Science Fellowship. I have experience ranging from full stack web development to theoretical research on methods.

# **EDUCATION**

# California Institute of Technology - Pasadena, CA

Oct 2017 - present

Ph.D. Candidate

Department of Computing and Mathematical Sciences, GPA: 3.9/4.0

Awarded NSF Graduate Research Fellowship and Amazon AI4Science Research Fellowship

# Cambridge University (Emmanuel College) - Cambridge, UK

Oct 2016 - Jun 2017

Mathematics Part 1B

Supported by a Herchel Smith Fellowship

Additional classes in Computer Science and Mathematics Part II

# Williams College - Williamstown, MA

Sep 2012 - Jun 2016

Bachelor of Arts

Majors: Physics and Computer Science, GPA: 3.92/4.00

Honors: Highest Honors (Physics), Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, Magna Cum Laude

Thesis: RNA Macrostates and Macrokinetics

### RESEARCH TOPICS

**Decision Fusion:** Many medical settings with privacy concerns deny direct access to data, requiring us to synthesize conclusions at a higher level. This setting is riddled with paradoxes - namely that conclusions are not necessarily transitive. We use "expert graphs" to define a new notion of consistency in networks of conclusions from differing contexts.

**Mixture Models for Causality:** Combining multiple populations or contexts induces universal confounding on a structural causal model (SCM). Assuming a bound on the cardinality of a discrete universal confounder turns the problem into a mixture model, allowing identification of within-source probability distributions. This perspective expands the notion of causal identifiability, as many graphically unidentifiable relationships can be identified.

**Domain Adaptation and Transportability:** I am interested in using causal principles to guide models that are robust to distribution shift. Our work uses concepts from causality and information theory to inform how auxiliary training tasks can separate causal and anticausal information from proxy variables.

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Amazon Research Causality Lab - Tübingen, Germany

Oct 2022 - Feb 2023

Applied Scientist Intern (L5)

Worked with Mila Hardt, Atalanti Mastakouri, and Dominik Janzing

Amazon's causality lab works in conjunction with software developers to research and develop causality-based products for AWS clients. My internship was research focused and I lead-authored a paper that was accepted to UAI 2023. I also gained experience with Amazon's code review process.

# BioDiscovery - El Segundo, CA

Jun 2017 - Sep 2017

Intern

BioDiscovery develops software for analyzing genomes. As an intern I developed methods for clustering cancers based on their genomes and implemented it within the company stack. My work has now been integrated into their software and presented at a conference.

# IBM T.J. Watson Research Center - Yorktown Heights, NY

Jun 2016 - Sep 2016

Intern

Worked with Dr. Victor Kravets (mentor) and Dr. Andrew Sullivan (manager).

Projects included non-greedy and map-reduce algorithms for factoring sum of products representations. The goal of this project was to find more efficient mappings of circuits onto 2-dimensional chips.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### **Markov Chain Monte Carlo**

Spring 2022

Head TA for Professor Leonard Schulman's new class.

# **Physics and Mathematics**

Sep 2013-Jun 2016

TAed for undergraduate classes in Electricity and Magnetism, Classical Mechanics, Mathematical Methods for Scientists, Premed Physics, Discrete Mathematics.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- **B.** Mazaheri, A. Mastakouri, D. Janzing, M. Hardt. "Causal Information Splitting: Engineering Proxy Features for Robustness to Distribution Shifts." UAI 2023 (to appear).
- S. Gordon, \*B. Mazaheri, Y. Rabani, L. Schulman. "Causal Inference Despite Limited Global Confounding via Mixture Models." CLeaR 2023.
- S. Jain, **B. Mazaheri**, N. Raviv, J. Bruck. "Glioblastoma signature in the DNA of blood-derived cells" PLoS ONE 16(9): e0256831. 2021.
- **B. Mazaheri**, S. Jain, J. Bruck. "Expert Graphs: Synthesizing New Expertise via Collaboration." IEEE ISIT 2021.
- S. Gordon, \*B. Mazaheri, Y. Rabani, L. Schulman. "Source Identification for Mixtures of Product Distributions." COLT 2021.
- **B. Mazaheri**, S. Jain, J. Bruck. "Robust Correction of Sampling Bias using Cumulative Distribution Functions." NeurIPS 2020.
- \* = Authorship order is alphabetical.

#### **PREPRINTS**

**B. Mazaheri**, S. Jain, M. Cook, J. Bruck. "Combining Binary Classifiers Leads to Nontransitive Paradoxes."

Accepted IEEE Transactions on Information Theory 2022 but retracted due to inability to attend conference in person.

- S. Gordon, \*B. Mazaheri, Y. Rabani, L. Schulman. "The Sparse Hausdorff Moment Problem, with Applications to Topic Models." arXiv 2020.
- S. Jain, **B. Mazaheri**, N. Raviv, J. Bruck. "Cancer Classification from Healthy DNA using Machine Learning." bioRxiv 2019.
- S. Jain, **B. Mazaheri**, N. Raviv, J. Bruck. "Short Tandem Repeats Information in TCGA is Statistically Biased by Amplification." bioRxiv 2019.
- \* = Authorship order in Theoretical CS is alphabetical. Co-authorship is implied.

### **PATENTS**

S. Jain, **B. Mazaheri**, N. Raviv, J. Bruck. "Mutation profile and related labeled genomic components, methods and systems." 2019.

# **PROJECTS**

LACCTiC.com Sep 2021 - present

I have developed a website for ranking collegiate cross country with 10,000 regular users. The website implements methods I have developed for adjusting performances in varying conditions. I've implemented the backend using Django, frontend using React, and host my database within an AWS framework.

#### AWARDS/GRANTS

# **National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship**

Awarded Spring 2019

Awarded in 2019 for a proposal to research confounding influence in causal networks.

# **Amazon AI4Science Research Fellowship**

Awarded Spring 2022

Funding for research with the potential to aid scientific discovery.

# WORKSHOPS

# Simon's Institute for Theory of Computing: Causality

Spring 2022

4 week workshop on Causal inference methods.

#### **TALKS**

# Simon's Institute for Theory of Computing: Causality Reunion

May 2023

Title: "Causal Discovery under Limited Global Confounding"

### **MENTORSHIP**

# **Caltech Cross Country Team**

Sep 2018 - present

Assistant Coach

Mentoring and supporting undergraduate students at Caltech.